<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<news><news_item><title>Tax threshold freeze not a pledge-breaker - Labour sources</title><published>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 04:50:33 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c79npj3eqdlo</link><summary>Government sources insist the move would not constitute a breach of Labour's manifesto tax pledge.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Boohoo considers break-up as sales slide</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 15:38:15 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/crkdynj42ldo</link><summary>The online fashion firm is mulling whether to offload its brands as sales remain under pressure.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>NHS consultant who lost £39k among 100 Revolut customers contacting BBC over scams</title><published>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 05:45:13 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c9wkzv1zk91o</link><summary>People say they have been poorly treated by the firm after being tricked out of cash while using app.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Who has to pay inheritance tax?</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 10:16:23 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-36014533</link><summary>Inheritance tax is again creating political debate so how does it work and who pays?</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Netflix raises prices as password boost fades</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 07:57:12 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cq5exj06vg6o</link><summary>The streaming giant will charge subscribers more in some countries to fuel growth.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Debt rule to change to fund major projects</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 09:15:25 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cvglyxn0444o</link><summary>Government claims the move contrasts with former PM Liz Truss's controversial mini-Budget.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Alleged Bitcoin hacker searched 'signs the FBI is after you'</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 10:08:10 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c20pvkg35xyo</link><summary>A man from Georgia is alleged to be part of a group which hacked the US regulator's X account.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>'It's our moonshot': Why scientists are drilling into volcanos</title><published>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 23:03:48 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c1e8q4j1yygo</link><summary>In Iceland scientists plan to drill down to magma to understand it and use it for energy production.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Faster grid hook-ups planned for some green energy projects</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 12:18:07 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly4kwep3kwo</link><summary>Wind farms ready to be built will be connected to the electricity grid quicker under government plans.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Fraudsters steal more than £3m a day as cases rise</title><published>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 23:01:11 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cglk7dlpwl5o</link><summary>Fraud cases rise by 16% in the first half of the year, but total losses are down slightly, new data shows.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Inheritance tax increases expected in Budget</title><published>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 20:40:34 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c8el3z910r9o</link><summary>It is not known how many people are likely to end up paying more under the government's plan.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>China's economic slowdown deepens</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 03:47:56 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/crr54x00857o</link><summary>Gross domestic product rose by 4.6% on a yearly basis, below Beijing's "around 5%" annual target.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Meta fires staff for buying toothpaste, not lunch</title><published>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 14:23:04 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cvgdyzq3wz5o</link><summary>Meta workers reportedly used vouchers that should have been spent on meals to buy household goods.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Ministers complain to Starmer over spending cuts</title><published>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 14:00:47 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c0r8e421y5po</link><summary>Some Cabinet members are alarmed at the scale of cuts being sought to plug a rumoured £40bn gap.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>US 'click to cancel' rule to ban subscription traps</title><published>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 03:34:56 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c07nlvmyl05o</link><summary>New rule requires businesses to make subscribing and cancelling subscriptions equally simple.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Surprise fall in inflation paves way for interest rate cuts</title><published>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 14:37:27 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/czxde3779lxo</link><summary>The drop to 1.7% paves the way for the Bank of England to cut interest rates again next month.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Why this month's inflation figure matters for you</title><published>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 12:32:44 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/czrmzm3113po</link><summary>The cost of living is always important but this month's has a particular extra impact for millions of people.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Mental health patients could get job coach visits</title><published>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 11:53:56 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c98y09n8201o</link><summary>Pensions Secretary Liz Kendall says trials of the idea have produced "dramatic results".</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Inside the £70k ‘mafia-style’ champagne shoplifting gang</title><published>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 01:21:08 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/czxdr29lyggo</link><summary>A crime gang has stolen more than £70,000 of goods from UK supermarkets in 18 months, the BBC hears.</summary></news_item><news_item><title>Reeves eyeing £40bn in tax rises and spending cuts</title><published>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 09:45:56 GMT</published><link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cj9jdgprv7ko</link><summary>Filling the £22bn financial "black hole" would only be enough “to keep public services" still, she told a meeting.</summary></news_item><content>An announcement in the upcoming budget of a continued freeze on income tax thresholds beyond 2028 would not constitute a breach of Labour's election manifesto promise, government sources have insisted.
In the run-up to June's general election, both leader Sir Keir Starmer and the soon-to-be Chancellor Rachel Reeves pledged to "not increase taxes on working people".
But a threshold freeze could allow the chancellor to raise an estimated £7bn by bringing more people into the tax system.
Reeves is currently trying to find £40bn through a mixture of savings and tax rises that she will announce in the new government's first budget on Wednesday 30 October.
Tax thresholds were frozen by the previous Conservative government in 2022, but were due to rise again each year from 2028.
The chancellor is now said to be weighing a plan to extend the freeze for the remainder of the parliament.
The decision not to increase tax thresholds would continue a process called "fiscal drag", in which more people are "dragged" into paying tax, or higher rates of tax, as their wages rise and cross the unchanging thresholds.
If Reeves goes ahead with the plan, roughly 400,000 more people will find themselves paying income tax at the basic rate.
Government insiders have insisted this does not breach Labour's manifesto pledge to "not increase taxes on working people".
Sources are pointing to the exact wording of the manifesto, which states that the "rates" of income tax would not rise.
In other words, in England, Wales and Northern Ireland these would remain – depending on income – at 20p, 40p and 45p.  
But as people's wages increased, so too would their tax bill.
In 2019, the Conservatives also pledged not to increase tax "rates" - and went on to freeze tax thresholds.
At the time, this was denounced by the Labour opposition as a "stealth tax".
However, it is not one the party has specifically pledged to reverse.
Labour's opponents will argue that an extension of a freeze would undermine the party’s wider-ranging promise not to increase taxes on working people.
Reeves has just 11 days to firm up her plans ahead of Budget day.
The country's first female chancellor has warned of a £22bn "black hole" in the public finances - a gap caused by the rules the government has chosen to follow governing how much money it can borrow over the next five years.
Filling this hole would only be enough to "keep public services standing still", the chancellor said this week.
This means she is hoping to find £40bn in order to avoid real-terms cuts to government departments. 
Reeves has warned of "difficult decisions" ahead.
The council votes to urge the prime minister to reverse the "dreadful" Winter Fuel Payment changes.
The government promise a “radical” shake-up of the welfare system to help people out of work due to sickness.
It is not known how many people are likely to end up paying more under the government's plan.
In his first visit to the north east since taking office, the minister vowed support for North Sea workers.
Some Cabinet members are alarmed at the scale of cuts being sought to plug a rumoured £40bn gap.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Boohoo is planning a major restructure that could see the break-up of the struggling online fashion firm whose brands include Debenhams, Karen Millen and PrettyLittleThing.
The company said it was reviewing options after concluding that its business remained "fundamentally undervalued".
While Boohoo benefited from the surge to online shopping during the pandemic, it has subsequently struggled against the likes of China's Shein and Temu.
Analysts said Boohoo was likely to focus on offloading Debenhams and Karen Millen to allow it to concentrate on a younger target market.
"The starting gun has been fired on the break-up of Boohoo," said Russ Mould, investment director at AJ Bell.
"Selling Karen Millen and Debenhams is the obvious starting point, leaving Boohoo with a sharper focus on a younger target market."
Retail analyst Catherine Shuttleworth added that fast-fashion firms were "under pressure" with shoppers thinking more sustainably and "making different choices".
Boohoo bought Karen Millen for £18.2m in 2019 and three years ago it took on department store brand Debenhams for £55m. 
"Acquired brands like Debenhams and Karen Millen, now purely online players, haven't had the impact on shoppers that the business might have liked," said Ms Shuttleworth. 
Boohoo admitted on Friday that its youth brands were struggling, including boohoo.com, boohooMAN and PrettyLittleThing, but said it expected that to improve in the second half of its financial year.
Meanwhile, the company said its chief executive, John Lyttle, would be leaving. He joined the firm six years ago from Primark.
Under Mr Lyttle, the business has attempted to shift its image away from fast fashion. In 2021, he told the BBC that Boohoo was not a "throwaway fashion brand" and the firm was aiming to be more sustainable.
But in 2023, a BBC Panorama investigation found Boohoo had broken promises to make its clothes fairly and ethically. An undercover reporter saw evidence of staff pressuring suppliers to drive prices down, even after deals had been agreed. 
Boohoo said at the time it had experienced significant cost inflation in the previous year and as costs had started to come down, it asked suppliers to reflect this in their pricing.
Earlier this year, the firm was found to have mislabelled some of its clothes, claiming they were made in the UK when they were actually made in South Asia. Boohoo said it was an isolated incident, which was down to a misinterpretation of  labelling rules.
On Friday, the company reported that its sales had fallen by 15% to £620m for the six months to the end of August. Trade tumbled across the UK, the US and internationally.
Ms Shuttleworth added that the core Boohoo shopper had "grown up".
"The generation behind is enjoying instore shopping and looking at alternative brands for inspiration," she said.

More than a quarter of shops are empty, but opinion is divided on how to find a long-term solution.
Megan Trapnell is making the items using surplus textiles from a luxury boat builder.
The free service will mean islanders can shop from retailers who do not currently ship to the Channel Islands.
Victoria's Secret Fashion Show was axed in 2019 after low ratings and criticism that it was sexist.
Stafford's Guildhall Shopping Centre will make way for a mix of shops and homes under the plans.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
“I never imagined I’d be a victim of a scam,” says Dr Ravi Kumar.
“But here I am, a 53-year-old NHS consultant in intensive care medicine and anaesthetics, deeply affected.”
He lost £39,000 in May when scammers tricked him into transferring money into his Revolut account and giving them access to it.
He'd been saving the money for his teenagers.
“I was very depressed,” he adds. “My children are too young to share this grief with.”
Dr Kumar is one of more than 100 people who have told the BBC they feel poorly treated by Revolut after being scammed, following a Panorama investigation into the e-money firm.
For him the deception started when he received a phone call from someone claiming to be from American Express, his credit card company. They told him that fraudulent activity had been detected on his account.
They said they would report this to the industry regulator and that he should expect another phone call from Barclays, his high street bank, as money in that account might also be at risk.
A few hours later he received a call from someone who said they were from Barclays.
They told him to transfer his savings to his Revolut account for safekeeping while they carried out repairs.
He didn’t. At this point, Dr Kumar was becoming suspicious.
He wanted the person on the end of the line to prove who they were.
He was given a number to call - and when he did, he heard a familiar Barclays welcome message, which reassured him.
But it was still the scammer on the phone.
They told him again to transfer his money to Revolut as a security measure - and this time, Dr Kumar agreed.
After the transfer the scammer asked him to delete the app for extra safety.
Little did he know that this would allow them to spend thousands of pounds from his account - without him getting any notifications.
The next morning Dr Kumar reinstalled the Revolut app on his phone and found his account drained of £39,000.
The 25 transactions that had been made included purchases of luxury fashion and technology items from companies such as Selfridges, Apple and Currys.
He contacted Revolut to complain but they told him in a letter, seen by the BBC, that he would not be refunded as he had ultimately authorised the scammers to use his card.
Dr Kumar has hired lawyers to submit his claim to the Financial Ombudsman Service (FOS), which settles complaints between consumers and finance companies.
“I don’t know how long I'll be able to pay for the legal help,” he says. “We cancelled two holidays, I've been working almost every Saturday since.”
He adds: “What’s even more disheartening than the financial loss is the indifference and lack of accountability displayed by Revolut.”
The e-money firm, founded in 2015 by two former bankers, has nine million customers in the UK and announced record annual profits last year of £438m.
Revolut was also named in more reports of fraud than any other major UK bank, according to figures collected last year by Action Fraud - the UK’s national reporting centre for fraud and cyber-crime.
In Dr Kumar’s case, the Revolut feature which enabled the scammers to spend his money was the ability to add his debit card to their digital wallet.
This allowed them to make purchases online without the need to check for details on his physical card.
This convenience, which is also offered by some other banks, is among a wide range of features which give Revolut a broad appeal.
Others include the option to hold money in different currencies, transfer it abroad, buy individual stocks, invest in commodities and access cryptocurrencies.
These features have helped Revolut - which describes itself as an “all-in-one finance app for your money” - become popular but it’s also what cyber security experts warn could be a weakness.
"It's like putting all your eggs in one basket,” says Prof Mark Button, who researches cybercrime.
“If you have a product which can link to all the different aspects of your financial life, and you get compromised by a fraud or scam, then that is highly dangerous.”
While Revolut offers many features - one thing it doesn’t have is an emergency phone number you can call to freeze your account. You have to ask them using their app’s chat function.
A dedicated phone number might have helped Lynne Elms stop scammers taking £160,000 in seven minutes from her employer.
She was working at her best friend’s cosmetics company in November 2022 when a scammer, who said they were from Revolut, told her the business’s account was under attack from fraudsters.
They said it was an emergency and she needed to move the money out of the account as soon as possible or risk losing it.
They convinced the 52-year-old to install a remote desktop application which they said would allow them to protect the account. It actually let them take control of her computer.
Over a period of seven minutes, the scammers pressured Lynne into authorising four transfers worth £160,000.
The accounts she was asked to transfer the money to had names including ‘refund’, ‘invoice’ and ‘cancel’.
It meant she saw these words in the notifications sent to her phone asking her to approve the transfers.
“Revolut were absolutely useless. It took me about three or four hours to get in touch with somebody,” says Lynne.
“Eventually Revolut froze the account. They told me there was nothing they could do. It felt like a one-liner to say sorry.”
Her employer has spent £70,000 on legal fees trying to get the money back.
An FOS investigator has recommended at least £115,000 should be refunded to them by Revolut, who are contesting the sum. A final decision by the Ombudsman is expected soon.
Revolut told us they were unable to comment on cases that were still ongoing with the FOS but said they were “sorry to hear about any instance where our customers are targeted by ruthless and highly sophisticated criminals”.
Addressing the fact that more than 100 people have contacted the BBC to complain about the firm, Revolut said such issues should be raised via their app.
They add that last year the number of fraudulent transactions using their service had been reduced by 20% and they had prevented £475m worth of potential fraud losses.
For victims who have lost money through scams on Revolut, the impact goes beyond financial stress.
“It felt like I was losing my business and my best friend,” says Lynne. “It was the worst time of my life. I never thought I'd get over it. I don’t think I have.”
Britain’s Newest Bank: How Safe Is Your Money?
Reporter Catrin Nye investigates the stories of Revolut customers who say scammers took tens of thousands of pounds from their accounts, and that Revolut failed to protect them.
Oliver Cooper is sentenced after forging signatures so he could defraud his former partner.
Inheritance tax is again creating political debate so how does it work and who pays?
The BBC's Colette Hume on her shock at hearing claims made by fraudulent nurse Tanya Nasir.
The cost of living is always important but this month's has a particular extra impact for millions of people.
Scammers are using fake codes to trick motorists into paying on unregistered sites, says council.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The prime minister and chancellor are considering changes to inheritance tax in order to raise more money, the BBC understands.
It is not known how many more people would pay the tax, or how much they would pay, under the changes planned as part of the 30 October Budget.
But who pays the tax now and how much does it raise?
Inheritance tax is charged at 40% on the property, possessions and money, external of somebody who has died, above a £325,000 threshold.
It is only charged on the part of the estate that lies above the threshold. For example, on an estate worth £335,000, the tax would apply to the additional £10,000.
There are a number of exemptions, as well as allowances for passing on a home to children, or grandchildren. 
Inheritance tax must be paid by the end of the sixth month after the person's death, otherwise interest will be charged too.
It currently raises about £7bn a year for the government.
The latest figures, external show that fewer than one in 20 estates - just over 4% - pay inheritance tax. It means the tax is paid on about 27,800 estates a year.
However, economists at the Institute for Fiscal Studies think tank predict that about 7% of estates could be liable for inheritance tax by 2032, external, under current rules.
Many more people than this believe they could be liable. A YouGov poll for The Times newspaper in July 2023 suggested a third thought inheritance tax would need to be paid on their assets when they died.
There are a number of reasons why a death does not result in payment of the tax.
They include:
Any estate that is valued at less than £325,000 (currently fixed until 2026)
Anyone who leaves their estate to a husband, wife or civil partner
Somebody who leaves it to certain charities or community sports clubs
Any land or pasture left in an estate that is used to grow crops or to rear animals
There are additional, significant allowances. 
If the person who dies leaves their home to their children or grandchildren the threshold goes up to £500,000.
Also, married or civil partners can transfer assets free of tax between each other, so one partner automatically inherits the other's unused allowance.
So the estate of someone who can use their late partner's allowance, and leaves a home to their children or grandchildren, won't be liable for inheritance tax on anything under £1m.
Anyone can give away up to £3,000 a year, and pay no tax. This is known as the annual exemption. If unused, this allowance can be carried over to the following year, up to a maximum of £6,000.  
In addition, if you can show that the gift was funded out of income - as opposed to savings - you will not pay inheritance tax. There are also allowances for wedding gifts.
However, if someone gives a bigger sum, then dies within seven years, then the money may be used as part of inheritance tax calculations.
It is thought changes to a number of exemptions are under consideration for the Budget, including the rules around gifts that are given while you are alive.
Inheritance tax increases expected in Budget
When is the Budget and what might be in it?
How much money does the government raise and spend?
Some parents set up a trust in favour of their child, which means they technically no longer own the assets, so they are free from inheritance tax.
But there are different types of trust and some complicated rules - here is the government's guide, external - so it is likely to be worth seeking independent advice.
There are lots of guides to inheritance tax from HM Revenue and Customs, external - which also has a helpline, and here on the Moneyhelper website, external.
Are autumn tax cuts really 'impossible'?
Why the state pension is going up by more than inflation
Fresh strikes in southern Beirut as Israel says Netanyahu's home targeted by drone
'You see us burning, you stay silent': Family’s agony over mother and sons burned to death in Gaza
Challenged on death of Dawn Sturgess, Russia’s ambassador appears to laugh and dismisses inquiry
'It got a little bit toxic': Liam Payne's hidden battles with fame
How will weight-loss drugs change our relationship with food?
The mates who have met for a pint every Thursday for 56 years
Angelina Jolie 'spellbinding' as opera star Callas
'Merchants of death' trial steps up fight against Channel smugglers
The Moon, twins and tributes to Liam: Photos of the week
The farmers targeted by false claims and threats over Harris ad
Why fight for justice isn't over in India's 'horrific' widow-burning case, 37 years on
Le Sserafim: The K-pop band who want to change the industry
Kit Harington stars in the new series of Industry
Plunge into the unrelenting, seductive world of high finance
Dame Maggie Smith leads in a poignant comedy-drama
Miss Shepherd ends up living on writer Alan Bennett's driveway in 1970s Camden
All the news as it happens, with Steve Coogan
Classic, savagely satirical award-winning comedy from an all-star cast
© 2024 BBC. The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
Netflix is starting to raise prices in some countries as growth spurred by its crackdown on password sharing starts to fade. 
The film and TV streaming giant said it had already lifted subscription fees in Japan and parts of Europe as well as the Middle East and Africa over the last month.
Changes in Italy and Spain are now being rolled-out.
In its latest results, Netflix announced that it had added 5.1 million subscribers between July and September - ahead of forecasts but the smallest gain in more than a year.
The company is under pressure to show investors what will power growth in the years ahead, as its already massive reach makes finding new subscribers more difficult.
The last time Netflix saw signs of slowdown, in 2022, it launched measures to stop password sharing and said it would offer a new streaming option with advertisements. 
The crackdown unleashed a new wave of growth. 
The firm has added more than 45 million new members since last year and has 282 million subscribers globally.
Analysts also expect advertisements to eventually become big business for Netflix. 
For now, however, Netflix has said it remains "early days" and warned it did not expect it to start driving growth until next year, despite many subscribers opting for the ad-supported plan.
The plan, which is the company's least expensive option, accounted for 50% of new sign-ups in the places where it is offered in the most recent quarter, Netflix said.
Even without a boost from advertising, Netflix said revenue in the July-September period was up 15% compared with the same period last year, to more than $9.8bn (£7.5bn). 
Profit also rose from $1.6bn in the same period last year to $2.3bn.
Netflix last raised prices in the UK and US in 2023 but that only affected certain plans. It has left the price of its popular "standard plan" without adverts untouched since 2022.
In the past, the company has sometimes experimented with pricing in smaller countries before making changes in major markets, such as the US and UK. 
Matt Britzman, senior equity analyst at Hargreaves Lansdown, said Netflix's strong financial position put the firm in a position to keep spending money to make new hits - the key if it hopes to raise prices without backlash. 
"This is inherently a fickle market, with consumers happy to swap streamer if they don’t think they’re getting value," he said. 
"The addition of fresh content is key to that, especially in areas like sporting events, and could give Netflix the edge it needs to push prices higher and keep customers coming back for more.”
One of Netflix's biggest successes has been Baby Reindeer, a drama created by and starring Scottish comedian Richard Gadd.
The controversial series won four Emmy Awards last month.
Netflix show allows actress to use Cardiff accent and explore her teen passion for Greek mythology.
Moon Music sells 237,000 in seven days, the best first-week sales by a British act since Adele's 30.
Charlie Covell responds to the streamer cancelling the popular comedy series this week.
Location filming for Heartstopper uses a real zoo, that is signed up to world conservation schemes.
A heritage watchdog says the planned plaque would be marking a show that was "no masterpiece".
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The Treasury has given its clearest indication yet it will change its self-imposed debt rule in order to borrow billions to fund new infrastructure projects.
Independent checks on spending for major building work will be introduced to allow the government to borrow for investment "more efficiently", the Treasury Chief Secretary, Darren Jones, has said.
He claimed the safeguards on spending will aim to avoid a repeat of the financial turmoil which followed the 2022 mini-Budget under former Prime Minister Liz Truss.
New watchdogs will oversee a 10-year strategy for a pipeline of major projects, in areas such as buildings, roads and rail.
What the government is calling the "guardrails" for infrastructure spending will form part of its aim to encourage the private sector to invest in British projects.
Under this plan, "expert-led checks and balances" will determine the quality of government borrowing for investment.
At the moment, the amount of money the government can borrow for investment is restrained by the amount of debt it has.
There is a self-imposed rule that debt – the total amount the government owes – must fall in five years’ time.
Many rich countries have similar rules, to keep government finances under control and maintain credibility with financial markets and taxpayers.
But the Treasury has effectively confirmed it will loosen the target in order to borrow billions more to invest in a range of major projects.
Ahead of the Budget on 30 October, Jones said the guardrails on spending would allow the government to borrow for investment "more efficiently going forward".
He said these guardrails were in contrast to the Truss government's "borrowing for unfunded policies". 
During her brief premiership in 2022, Truss used her mini-Budget to unveil £45bn in unfunded tax cuts in an attempt to boost economic growth.
Jones said: "We need expert, institutional and some independent guardrails to make sure everybody has confidence in the way that the government is spending taxpayer money.
"What I'm confirming today is we put those in place for capital investment and infrastructure delivery."
The changes will include a new National Infrastructure and Service Transformation Authority that will oversee a 10-year strategy for a pipeline of major projects, aligned with a series of Spending Reviews, and long-term budgets for investment in, for example, buildings, roads and rail.
The National Audit Office and a new Office for Value for Money will also offer ongoing appraisals of “mega projects” such as major train lines.
The government said the moves would “depoliticise” infrastructure decisions and offer “independent checks and balances” against government, similar to the Office for Budget Responsibility.
In the government’s view this system will provide an independent quality control on major projects spending, that has been beset with delay and overspend, and proved more expensive in the UK than other major economies.
Ministers argue that the current debt rule has led to poor quality UK public services by constraining some necessary investment, and has also allowed spending on failing projects.
A Cabinet minister told the BBC: “When we do invest in projects we will make sure they deliver genuine value for money, they bring a return on investment and they deliver for communities.
"The Conservatives wasted billions of taxpayers’ pounds on ministerial pet projects that never delivered and were about trying to buy votes. The Budget will be about changing that.” 
The announcement comes as the government faces scrutiny over how it will choose to spend money in the Budget at the end of October.
On Wednesday, several ministers wrote to the prime minister to call for an eleventh-hour rethink of the spending review, which they worry will see their departments' budgets slashed.
Those reportedly concerned included Deputy Prime Minister Angela Rayner, Justice Secretary Shabana Mahmood, and Transport Secretary Louise Haigh.
Jones's comments come alongside the government's introduction of a "taskforce" for infrastructure spending - a group of private sector bosses including from HSBC, Lloyds and M&amp;G - who will advise government on where to invest for infrastructure.
The government has said its top priority is boosting growth in the UK's economy, and the Chancellor, Rachel Reeves, said increasing investment in infrastructure was a "vital part" of achieving this. 
On Monday, Prime Minister Sir Keir Starmer hosted a major investment summit to try to attract billions of pounds into the UK from international investors.
He told the summit he would scrap regulation that "holds back investment" and would ask regulators to prioritise economic growth.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
A man arrested in connection with a hack of the US markets regulator's X account searched "how can I know for sure if I am being investigated by the FBI," according to court documents.
Eric Council Jr, 25, of Athens, Georgia, is also alleged to have searched for "signs that you are under investigation by law enforcement... even if you have not been contacted by them".
He is accused of being part of a group which hacked the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) social media in January to make a fake post about Bitcoin, causing the cryptocurrency to surge in value.
The regulator previously admitted a key security step to access its X account had been removed. 
The post sent by hackers on the SEC's X account made the false claim the regulator had allowed Bitcoin to be part of mainstream investment funds.
This caused the price of the cryptocurrency to rise by about $1,000 (£770), according to the US Department of Justice, before falling by $2,000 when it was found to be untrue.
Despite the confusion caused by the hack, the SEC later approved Bitcoin to be a part of mainstream investment, through what are known as spot Bitcoin exchange-traded funds.
According to court documents, Eric Council Jr went under the aliases Ronin, Easymunny, and AGiantSchnauzer online, and searched "SECGOV hack" and "Telegram sim swap".
He is also alleged to have searched "federal identity theft statute" and "how long does it take to delete Telegram account".
Telegram is a messaging app with more than 950 million monthly active users.
The SEC has confirmed its account was compromised by a Sim swap attack.
This is when someone fraudulently gets a mobile phone carrier to apply an existing telephone number to a new Sim card.
In this case, the alleged perpetrator is accused of creating a fake ID with the details of an SEC employee which were passed on to him by co-conspirators.
He is then alleged to have used these details to get the employee's mobile number transferred to a new Sim.
Co-conspirators are alleged to have used access codes sent to the phone to login to the SEC's X account.
This was made easier due to a lack of adequate protection on the account.
SEC staff had asked X in July 2023 to suspend multi-factor authentication (MFA), a security measure used to help verify the person logging in.
It subsequently re-enabled MFA after the hack.
Eric Council Jr is charged with one count of conspiracy to commit aggravated identity theft and access device fraud.
If found guilty, he could face up to five years in prison. 
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
I'm in one of the world's volcanic hotspots, northeast Iceland, near the Krafla volcano.
A short distance away I can see the rim of the volcano's crater lake, while to the south steam vents and mud pools bubble away.
Krafla has erupted around 30 times in the last 1,000 years, and most recently in the mid-1980s.
Bjorn Guðmundsson leads me to a grassy hillside.  He is running a team of international scientists who plan to drill into Krafla's magma.
“We’re standing on the spot where we are going to drill,” he says.
The Krafla Magma Testbed (KMT) intends to advance the understanding of how magma, or molten rock, behaves underground. 
That knowledge could help scientists forecast the risk of eruptions and push geothermal energy to new frontiers, by tapping into an extremely hot and potentially limitless source of volcano power.
Starting in 2027 the KMT team will begin drilling the first of two boreholes to create a unique underground magma observatory, around 2.1km (1.3 miles) under the ground.
“It's like our moonshot. It's going to transform a lot of things,” says Yan Lavallée, a professor of magmatic petrology and volcanology at the Ludwigs-Maximillian University in Munich, and who heads KMT’s science committee.
Volcanic activity is usually monitored by tools like seismometers. But unlike lava on the surface, we don’t know very much about the magma below ground, explains Prof Lavallée.
“We'd like to instrument the magma so we can really listen to the pulse of the earth,” he adds.
Pressure and temperature sensors will be placed into the molten rock. “These are the two key parameters we need to probe, to be able to tell ahead of time what's happening to the magma," he says.
Around the world an estimated 800 million people live within 100km of hazardous active volcanoes. The researchers hope their work can help save lives and money.
Iceland has 33 active volcano systems, and sits on the rift where the Eurasian and North American tectonic plates pull apart.
Most recently, a wave of eight eruptions in the Reykanes peninsula has damaged infrastructure and upended lives in the community of Grindavik.
Mr Guðmundsson also points to Eyjafjallajökull, which caused havoc in 2010 when an ash cloud caused over 100,000 flight cancellations, costing £3bn ($3.95bn).
“If we’d been better able to predict that eruption, it could have saved a lot of money,” he says.
KMT’s second borehole will develop a test-bed for a new generation of geothermal power stations, which exploit magma's extreme temperature.
“Magma are extremely energetic. They are the heat source that power the hydrothermal systems that leads to geothermal energy. Why not go to the source?” asks Prof Lavallée.
Some 25% of Iceland’s electricity and 85% of household heating, comes from geothermal sources, which tap hot fluids deep underground, making steam to drive turbines and generate electricity.
In the valley below, the Krafla power plant supplies hot water and electricity to about 30,000 homes.
“The plan is to drill just short of the magma itself, possibly poke it a little bit,” says Bjarni Pálsson with a wry smile.
"The geothermal resource is located just above the magma body, and we believe that is around 500-600C,” says Mr Pálsson, the executive director of geothermal development at national power provider, Landsvirkjun.
Magma is very hard to locate underground, but in 2009 Icelandic engineers made a chance discovery.
They had planned to make a 4.5km deep borehole and extract extremely hot fluids, but the drill abruptly stopped as it intercepted surprisingly shallow magma.
“We were absolutely not expecting to hit magma at only 2.1km depth,” says Mr Pálsson.
Encountering magma is rare and has only happened here, Kenya and Hawaii.
Superheated steam measuring a recording-breaking 452°C shot up, while the chamber was an estimated 900°C.
Dramatic video shows billowing smoke and steam. Acute heat and corrosion eventually destroyed the well.
“This well produced about 10 times more [energy] than the average well in this location,” says Mr Pálsson. 
Just two of these could supply the same energy as the power plant’s 22 wells, he notes. “There is an obvious game changer.”
More than 600 geothermal power plants are found worldwide, and hundreds more are planned, amid growing demand for round-the-clock low carbon energy. These wells are typically around 2.5km deep, and handle temperatures below 350°C.
Private companies and research teams in several countries are also working towards more advanced and ultra-deep geothermal, called super-hot rock, where temperatures exceed 400°C at depths of 5 to 15km.
Reaching deeper and much hotter, heat reserves is the "Holy Grail", says Rosalind Archer, the dean of Griffith University, and former director of the Geothermal Institute in New Zealand.
It’s the higher energy density that’s so promising, she explains, as each borehole can produce five to 10 times more power than standard geothermal wells.
“You've got New Zealand, Japan and Mexico all looking, but KMT is the closest one to getting drill bit in the ground,” she says. “It's not easy and it's not necessarily cheap to get started.”
Drilling into this extreme environment will be technically challenging, and requires special materials.
Prof Lavallée is confident it’s possible. Extreme temperatures are also found in jet engines, metallurgy and the nuclear industry, he says.
“We have to explore new materials and more corrosion resistant alloys,” says Sigrun Nanna Karlsdottir, a professor of industrial and mechanical engineering at the University of Iceland.
Inside a lab, her team of researchers are testing materials to withstand extreme heat, pressure and corrosive gases. Geothermal wells are usually constructed with carbon steel, she explains, but that quickly loses strength when temperatures exceed 200°C.
“We’re focusing on high grade nickel alloys and also titanium alloys,” she says.
Drilling into volcanic magma sounds potentially risky, but Mr Guðmundsson thinks otherwise.
“We don’t believe that sticking a needle into a huge magma chamber is going to create an explosive effect,” he asserts.
“This happened in 2009, and they found out that they’d probably done this before without even knowing it. We believe it’s safe.”
Other risks also need to be considered when drilling into the earth like toxic gases and causing earthquakes, says Prof Archer.  “But the geological environment in Iceland makes that very unlikely.”
The work will take years, but could bring advanced forecasting and supercharged volcano power.
“I think the whole geothermal world are watching the KMT project,” says Prof Archer. “It is potentially quite transformative.”
Neart na Gaoithe wind farm off the coast of Fife is expected to be completed by next summer.
The streaming giant will charge subscribers more in some countries to fuel growth.
Gross domestic product rose by 4.6% on a yearly basis, below Beijing's "around 5%" annual target.
In his first visit to the north east since taking office, the minister vowed support for North Sea workers.
Plans to build five 180m high wind turbines are given the go-ahead by the Welsh government.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Wind and solar farms that are ready to be built would be allowed to jump the queue for a connection to the UK’s electricity system under government plans.
All energy schemes which need a connection to the National Grid are currently in a single queue which operates on a "first-come-first-served" basis.
Some projects face waiting times stretching long into the next decade to get connected.
The government wants to speed up projects that will help it meet its goal of decarbonising power generation in the UK by 2030.
Some industry sources say it would be a welcome move but others warn that there is a “real risk” of legal challenges from projects which lose out.
The previous government brought in powers to weed out projects from the queue which were not ready to start, under a “first ready, first connected” system.
It followed complaints that so-called “zombie projects,” which have little or no chance of being built, are blocking the way of those which are ready to go. 
Now plans are under way for the creation of what is essentially a new grouping of energy projects, which will run on a “first ready and needed, first connected” system, leapfrogging over other projects in the queue.
The “needed” element refers to projects which are needed for clean power by 2030.
The plans are being developed by the National Energy System Operator (NESO), a new publicly-owned body tasked with connecting generation projects to the grid.
They would need to be approved by the energy regulator Ofgem, with connections intended to start by the end of 2025.
NESO said: “This is a complex challenge, and it's important we get it right.”
But the industry is calling for more clarity, amid concerns about legal challenges from companies waiting to get connected in the current queue who may find their dates are being pushed back.
Charles Wood, deputy director of Energy UK, said it was "positive" that the government appeared to have acknowledged the threat of legal challenges. 
But he said he would like to see more engagement from senior ministers to “address uncertainty” about the plans for network upgrades.
Merlin Hyman, chief executive of energy think tank Regen, said the plans to allow some projects to jump the queue made “a lot of sense” as the current system was "not fit for purpose".
But he added: “Such a fundamental change is inevitably causing uncertainty for project developers and we need urgently to provide the clarity and certainty needed to unlock investment at the speed and scale required”.
It comes after initial attempts to purge the existing queue for connection of so-called “zombie projects” resulted in only 10 GW of connection being struck off, according to the Energy Networks Association.
This year, Ofgem put the size of the existing queue at 701 GW, and it’s expected to reach 800 GW by the end of 2024, which is far more than the UK would need by 2050.
A Department for Energy Security and Net Zero spokesperson said it planned to submit proposals for reform to Ofgem by the end of the year.
“This includes speeding up the process and reforming the system to remove stalled projects from the queue, so projects which support our 2030 clean power goal can be connected fast,” the spokesperson added.
Barry Lewis and other campaigners want to make Amber Valley a National Landscape designation.
Jenny Pennington said Mr Miliband should buy her house after he said he was happy living by pylons.
The platform wants customers to go 'green' as it tries to boost the take-up of electric cars.
The free calculator helps businesses to cut CO2 as they move towards Net Zero by 2050.
National Grid says building a network of pylons is "significantly" cheaper than underground cables.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Fraud cases have risen by 16% with con artists stealing more than £3m a day, according to figures from the banking industry.
Criminals have particularly targeted victims by tricking them out of their one-time passcodes, trade body UK Finance said.
Despite the increase in reported cases, total losses have fallen slightly - totalling £572m in the first half of the year.
Banks said that fraud posed a "major threat" to the UK and called for support in tackling the crime.
The figures come after BBC Panorama revealed earlier this week a stream of cases involving e-money firm Revolut.
One victim told of how he lost £165,000 from his business account within an hour. Revolut said it had "robust controls" in place.
Changing tactics by fraudsters have seen cases rise in the first six months of this year, compared with the same period last year. 
Unauthorised payments rose sharply, with losses up 5%, driven in part by fraudsters circumventing protection systems.
When a customer makes a payment online, they are often sent a one-time passcode to verify the transaction.
Fraudsters have found ways to trick people into telling them these codes, in order to steal money.
However, the latest data shows there were relatively large falls in romance and investment scams.
This may have been the result of the promise of stricter rules regarding so-called authorised push payment (APP) fraud prevention. 
When criminals dupe their victims into sending them money by pretending to be a legitimate company, such as their bank or a tradesperson, or by selling goods that do not exist, this is known as APP fraud.
New mandatory rules took effect on 7 October which will see UK banks refund APP fraud victims up to £85,000 within five days.
Before the compulsory rules came in, most banks had signed up to a voluntary reimbursement code.
There were 97,344 cases of APP fraud in the first half of the year, with total losses of £214m. 
“Fraud continues to pose a major threat in this country," said Ben Donaldson, managing director of economic crime at UK Finance.
"In addition to the financial impact, this crime can cause severe psychological harm to victims. 
"This isn’t a fight we will win alone."
On Sunday, Charlie Nunn, chief executive of Lloyds Banking Group, accused Meta, the tech giant which owns social media platforms Facebook and Instagram, of "enabling" people to be contacted by fraudsters running online scams.
Meta said in response that its "pilot Fraud Intelligence Reciprocal Exchange programme (FIRE)" was designed to enable banks to "share information so we can work together to protect people using our respective services".
Oliver Cooper is sentenced after forging signatures so he could defraud his former partner.
The council votes to urge the prime minister to reverse the "dreadful" Winter Fuel Payment changes.
Inheritance tax is again creating political debate so how does it work and who pays?
Chancellor Rachel Reeves will set out the government's financial plans for the next year.
A project in Kent is offering local people a home-made lunch for what they can afford. 
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The government is planning to increase the amount of money it raises in inheritance tax at the Budget, the BBC has learned.
It is not known how many people are likely to end up paying more, nor how much more they would pay.
It is understood the prime minister and the chancellor are considering multiple changes to the tax, which currently includes several exemptions and reliefs.
Inheritance tax is charged at 40% on the property, possessions and money of somebody who has died above the £325,000 threshold. 
It raises about £7bn a year for the government.
Around 4% of deaths result in an inheritance tax charge.
The tax includes a series of exemptions which over the years several governments have considered changing in order to raise more money.
It is thought changes to a number of these are under consideration.
Current exemptions and reliefs include rules around gifts that are given while you are alive.
Gifts given less than seven years before you die may be taxed.
There is also Business Relief for Inheritance Tax, and Agricultural Relief, which allows land or pasture that is used to grow crops or to rear animals to be free of Inheritance Tax.
It is not known what changes will be made in the Budget on Wednesday, 30 October.
A spokesman for the Treasury told the BBC: “We do not comment on speculation around tax changes outside of fiscal events.”
Ministers are attempting to plug what they claim is a £40bn shortfall between what they want to spend and the amount of tax they expect to collect.
Government sources say it is vital there is a “reset in the public finances” and are keen to emphasise what they see as the “scale of the challenge".
This can be seen as part of the expectation management ahead of Rachel Reeves’ address.
Most new governments put up taxes immediately after a general election.
The Budget is expected to be billed as “Fixing the Foundations to Deliver Change".
Both the prime minister and the chancellor have already appeared in front of lecterns branded “Fixing the Foundations” – an attempt to highlight what they claim is the mess they inherited from the Conservatives.
For several weeks, senior government figures have been strongly hinting that there will be increases to the amount of National Insurance paid by employers.
The Labour manifesto before the general election said that “Labour will not increase taxes on working people, which is why we will not increase National Insurance, the basic, higher, or additional rates of Income Tax, or VAT".
This massively limits their options to raise more tax revenue.
But ministers appear willing to stretch the spirit if not the letter of their promise by putting up National Insurance on employers, some of whom – smaller businesses - would probably regard themselves as working people.
The chancellor is expected to give herself extra breathing space by changing the government’s self imposed rules on when it can borrow money, and has told some government departments that their budgets will be lower than they want.
A Labour source said that the negotiations on spending had provoked “significant angst” across the cabinet.
Shadow Chancellor Jeremy Hunt told the BBC: “During the election we repeatedly warned that Labour's sums didn't add up and that they were planning to raise taxes. The real scandal is that despite planning these tax rises all along, they didn't have the courage to admit it to the public during the election campaign.
"Unfortunately, it looks like it will be people who have saved all their life to provide an inheritance to their family who will pay the price for Labour's tax rises.”
Sign up for our Politics Essential newsletter to read top political analysis, gain insight from across the UK and stay up to speed with the big moments. It’ll be delivered straight to your inbox every weekday.
The BBC has learned the UK government is planning to increase the amount of money it raises through inheritance tax.
Chancellor Rachel Reeves will set out the government's financial plans for the next year.
Government claims the move contrasts with former PM Liz Truss's controversial mini-Budget.    
Safeguarding minister Jess Phillips aims to clear a backlog of more than 23,000 cases.
In his first visit to the north east since taking office, the minister vowed support for North Sea workers.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
China's economy expanded in the third quarter at the slowest pace since early last year, as the country struggles to boost flagging growth.
On an annual basis, gross domestic product (GDP) rose by 4.6% in the three months to the end of September, according to China's National Bureau of Statistics. 
That is less than the previous quarter and below the government's "around 5%" target for this year.
But it was slightly better than analysts expected, while other official figures released on Friday, including retail sales and factory output, also beat forecasts.
In recent weeks, Beijing has announced a number of measures aimed at supporting growth.
This is the second quarter in a row that China's official measure of economic growth has fallen below the 5% target, which will add to government concerns.
"The government’s growth target for this year now appears in serious jeopardy," the former head of the International Monetary Fund's (IMF) China division, Eswar Prasad told BBC News.
"It will take a substantial stimulus-fuelled boost to growth in the fourth quarter to hit the target."
But Moody's Analytics' economist, Harry Murphy Cruise, was more optimistic. The stimulus measures are "likely to propel the economy to its around 5% target for the year", he said.
"But more is required if officials are to address the structural challenges in the economy."
Official figures also showed new home prices fell in September at the fastest pace in almost a decade, indicating that the downturn in the property sector is worsening.
"The property market unsurprisingly remains the biggest drag on China's growth," said Lynn Song, chief economist for greater China at banking giant ING.
"New investment is unlikely to see a substantive recovery until prices stabilise and housing inventories decline... until then property will remain a notable headwind to growth."
Earlier on Friday, China's central bank said it had held a meeting to call on banks and other financial institutions to boost lending to help support growth.
Last month, the People's Bank of China (PBOC) announced the country's biggest stimulus package since the pandemic, including large cuts to interest and mortgage rates.
The plans also included help for the flagging stock market and measures to encourage banks to lend more to businesses and individuals.
Since then, the Ministry of Finance and other government bodies have unveiled further plans aimed at boosting economic growth.
The world's second largest economy has been hit by a number of challenges, including a property crisis, as well as weak consumer and business confidence.
David Lammy's low-key visit to Beijing shows the party is still trying to work out its China stance.
The US Treasury announces the move after the Ukrainian president called out China's involvement in Russian arms.
The rate at which prices are rising has dropped below the Bank of England's target of 2%.
Beijing says the exercise involved all parts of the military and simulates a full-scale attack on its neighbour.
China sees Taiwan as a breakaway province, but the self-ruled island sees itself as distinct.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Workers at Meta have reportedly been sacked for abusing the tech firm's meal voucher system, such as using it to buy toothpaste and washing powder.
Other breaches of the policy included sharing the vouchers with others or going over budget, according to people who said they work at Meta.
There are differing accounts over how much warning, if any, the owner of Instagram, Facebook and WhatsApp gave the workers before firing them.
Separately, the company has reportedly cut jobs across the business. Meta has been contacted for comment.
Meta staff are given $25 (£19) for lunch, $20 for breakfast, and $25 for dinner in vouchers which are meant to be used for ordering food from Grubhub, the US name for takeaway website Just Eat.
Posts on anonymous work social message board Blind appear to confirm elements of the story, originally reported by the Financial Times.
One user wrote that more than 30 people were fired last week because they used the credits for "non-food items, shared credits with people, or went above budget".
Examples of the non-food items bought included toothpaste, toothbrushes and wine glasses.
"They were given a warning to stop which most of them did, but were still fired three months later even after stopping," the user said.
Some repeated the claim the staff were warned, though other users wrote that there were no warnings.
Separately, the company has also reportedly made job cuts at WhatsApp, Instagram and Reality Labs, its virtual reality business responsible for the Oculus headset. These cuts are not related to the issues surrounding the voucher system. 
Jane Manchun Wong, a former security engineer at Meta, said on Wednesday that she had lost her job as part of these wider layoffs.
"I’m still trying to process this but I’m informed that my role at Meta has been impacted," she wrote on X, formerly Twitter.
Ms Wong was hired just over a year ago as a software engineer after making 2022's Forbes 30 under 30 list.
The layoffs were first reported by Verge, with a spokesperson telling the tech publication: "A few teams at Meta are making changes to ensure resources are aligned with their long-term strategic goals and location strategy.
“This includes moving some teams to different locations, and moving some employees to different roles. In situations like this when a role is eliminated, we work hard to find other opportunities for impacted employees."
Law enforcement have reported a rise in sextortion scams targeting teens across online platforms.
The couple who relied on their page to take 80% of their bookings say they are "overjoyed". 
Privacy activist Max Schrems claimed Meta unlawfully processed data relating to his sexual orientation.


An inquiry was launched in April 2019 by the Irish Data Protection Commission.
The firm also unveiled the first working prototype of Meta's augmented-reality glasses, called Orion.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Several cabinet ministers have written to the prime minister and the Treasury two weeks ahead of the Budget, to voice concerns over the scale of cuts their departments may face.
There are fears that steep spending cuts will be needed to meet what Whitehall sources have suggested is a £40bn funding gap.
In what some say is an unusual move, ministers from hard-pressed departments are calling for a last-minute rethink of the Budget, “going over the head” over the chancellor, to address the prime minister directly.
Overall spending totals have been agreed by the prime minister and chancellor, with Downing Street saying: "Not every department will be able to do everything they want to."
There has been considerable Cabinet disquiet about the spending cuts required to meet the Treasury’s proposed spending limit.
Bloomberg reported that ministers had expressed concern that the proposed cuts could be as high as 20% next year.
They reportedly include Deputy Prime Minister Angela Rayner who runs the Ministry of Housing, Communities and Local Government, as well as Justice Secretary Shabana Mahmood and Transport Secretary Louise Haigh. None of the ministers denied the report.
Haigh refused to comment on the reports, but told the BBC: "Budget negotiations and discussions are taking places across government in absolutely the usual way."
She added that she was "looking forward to the chancellor's announcement" on 30 October.
Responding to the speculation, the prime minister’s official spokesperson said public services needed “reform” and government departments will have to “become more productive”.
Sir Keir Starmer and Rachel Reeves have agreed on the spending totals to be unveiled in the budget on 30 October, the spokesman said.
But negotiations are ongoing with individual departments about their specific allocations, the spokesman added.
Danny Shaw, a commentator on justice and policing affairs, who has previously advised the Home Secretary Yvette Cooper, said cuts of that order would be "devastating" for the justice department.
"It would completely destroy in many ways the criminal justice system in terms of the courts, probation, prisons and legal aid," he said.
There is already a backlog of around 68,000 cases in the crown courts, he added.
A Labour source told the BBC that there was “significant angst” across government at a failure from the Treasury to “recognise the trade-offs” of cutting spending.
A former senior aide to Conservative chancellors during multiple Budgets said that they had never experienced a cabinet minister “going over our head” to the prime minister.
However, a Downing Street source said exchanges like this were were a “completely normal part of the process”, and denied that it is unusual for cabinet ministers to address their concerns to the prime minister rather than the chancellor.
Education Secretary Bridget Phillipson declined to comment on whether she was part of the group that had written to Sir Keir Starmer and the Treasury.
“There are lots of conversations happening right now across government between the chancellor with members of the Cabinet as you would expect in the usual way as part of the Budget process,” she told BBC Radio 4's Today programme.
Asked whether her department was protected from spending cuts, she said that “education is always a priority for Labour governments”.
Filling the gap in funding public services could lead to the largest tax raising Budget in a generation when Chancellor Rachel Reeves makes her statement at the end of this month.
Reeves has decided to commit to a new borrowing rule that means day-to-day spending must be covered by tax revenues.
As the government insists it will stick to manifesto promises not to raise taxes on working people, the focus is now on the extension of National Insurance to employer pensions contributions and increases in some form of capital gains tax.
There is also speculation that amid falling petrol prices, there is a possibility of higher fuel taxes.
Sign up for our Politics Essential newsletter to read top political analysis, gain insight from across the UK and stay up to speed with the big moments. 
It’ll be delivered straight to your inbox every weekday.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The US Federal Trade Commission (FTC) has adopted a 'click to cancel' rule, which aims to make it easier for people to end subscriptions.
It will force companies to make subscription sign-ups and cancellations equally straightforward.
Businesses, including retailers and gyms, will also have to get consent from customers before renewing subscriptions or converting free trials into paid memberships.
The new rule is due to come into effect in around six months' time.
“Too often, businesses make people jump through endless hoops just to cancel a subscription,” said FTC chair Lina Khan. 
“The FTC’s rule will end these tricks and traps, saving Americans time and money. Nobody should be stuck paying for a service they no longer want.”
Under the new rule, businesses will be banned from forcing customers to go though a chatbot or an agent to cancel subscriptions that were originally signed up to using an app or website 
For memberships that customers signed up to in person, businesses will have to offer the option to terminate them by calling by phone or online.
Last year, the FTC took legal action against technology giant Amazon on a related issue.
The lawsuit accused the firm of tricking customers into signing up for Prime subscriptions that renewed automatically and made it difficult for people to cancel.
It also said Amazon's website designs pushed customers into agreeing to enrol in Prime and have the subscription automatically renewed as they were making purchases.
Amazon has rejected the claims.
The FTC has also taken legal action against software giant Adobe for similar reasons.
It sued the company for allegedly violating consumer protection laws with "hidden" termination fees and a convoluted cancellation process.
The FTC said Adobe had failed to clearly disclose its terms to customers, including the year-long length of a subscription and charges that would be triggered for cancelling early.
Adobe has disputed the allegations.
A law introduced in the UK in May also takes aim at so-called subscriptions traps. 
The Digital Markets, Competition and Consumers Act 2024 requires businesses to provide clear information to consumers before they enter a subscription agreement.
It forces sellers to remind customers that a free or low-cost trial is coming to an end.
It also requires companies to ensure customers can easily end a contract.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
UK inflation fell unexpectedly to 1.7% in the year to September, the lowest rate in three-and-a-half years.
It means the annual rate prices are rising at is now below the Bank of England's 2% target, paving the way for further interest rate cuts.
Lower airfares and petrol prices were the main drivers behind the surprise slowdown, official figures showed.
Separately, September's inflation figure is also normally used to set how much many benefits will rise by next April.
UK interest rates are currently at 5%. The Bank made a first cut in August but decided to hold them last month. 
It is already widely expected that they will be cut in November.
But the lower-than-expected inflation rate has also opened the door for a December cut too, according to Susannah Streeter, of investment firm Hargreaves Lansdown.
Danni Hewson, head of financial analysis at AJ Bell, said a 0.25 percentage point cut was "pretty much nailed on" for November and expectations of a second cut in December had "jumped up".
Yael Selfin, chief economist at KPMG UK, warned that although the Bank would be likely to drop rates next month, inflation is likely to rise again with household energy bills increasing this month by around 10%.
The Bank's base interest rate heavily influences the rates High Street banks and other money lenders charge customers for loans, as well as credit cards.
The higher level has meant people are paying more to borrow money for things like mortgages, but savers have also received better returns. Increased mortgage repayments for landlords can also result higher rents.
The cost of living has surged in recent years, with inflation peaking at 11% in 2022 - way above the Bank of England's 2% target, partly due to the increase in energy prices following Russia's invasion of Ukraine.
To try to slow price rises, the Bank increased rates to encourage people to spend less, and bring inflation down.
While the rate has dropped, falling inflation does not mean the goods and services are coming down in price overall, it is just that they are rising at a slower pace.
Maria is a helper at a St Andrew’s Community Network food pantry in Liverpool where people pay £3.50 a week to get fresh groceries and tinned goods worth about £25.
She also uses the food pantry, and says life would be "really difficult" without it.
Maria is able to take her kids out "once in a blue moon" when she has money left over, "but I’ve got to prioritise food, heating, gas, lecky".
"I’ve noticed the prices in Asda and Aldi’s gone right up," she said. "You don’t get enough money to cover it."
The surprise fall in inflation last month to 1.7, down from 2.2% in August, was mainly driven by airfares and fuel.
Petrol and diesel prices were significantly lower, dropping by 10.4% in September compared with the same month a year earlier.
Airfare prices for domestic, European and long-haul flights normally fall after the summer rush, but they fell more than normal last month.
However, food and non-alcoholic drink prices rose, with costs jumping for milk, cheese, eggs, soft drinks and fruit.
This was the first time food price inflation has risen March last year.
Chief secretary to the Treasury, Darren Jones, said the drop in the pace of price rises overall would be "welcome news for millions of families".
He added that the government is "focused on bringing back growth and restoring economic stability to deliver on the promise of change".
The surprise fall in the UK's inflation rate comes ahead of this month's Budget, with Chancellor Rachel Reeves looking to make tax rises and spending cuts to the value of £40bn.
Reeves, who is finalising details of her first Budget on 30 October, warned ministers there would be "difficult decisions on spending, welfare, and tax".
She is drawing up plans to find £40bn to avoid real-terms cuts to government departments, sources have said.
September's inflation data is normally used to calculate how much many benefits go up in April.
This includes the biggest: universal credit, which goes up at the government's discretion.
All the main disability benefits - personal independence payment, attendance allowance and disability living allowance - as well as carer’s allowance, go up by at least September's inflation rate by law.
The government has said it wants to shrink the UK's annual disability and incapacity benefits bill.
A rise of 1.7% for benefits would be less than April's expected rise in the state pension of 4.1%, which is determined by the so-called triple lock.
Government sources insist the move would not constitute a breach of Labour's manifesto tax pledge.
The government promise a “radical” shake-up of the welfare system to help people out of work due to sickness.
Chancellor Rachel Reeves will set out the government's financial plans for the next year.
Some Cabinet members are alarmed at the scale of cuts being sought to plug a rumoured £40bn gap.
Bank of England interest rates affect the mortgage, loan and savings rates for millions of people.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The cost of living is always important to our finances but this month's has a particular extra impact for millions of people.
The September inflation figure, showing the rates at which prices increase, will  affect how much benefits and the state pension will rise as well as influencing interest rates and the prices in shops.
It also comes just two weeks before this government's first Budget, with the chancellor warning there will be “difficult decisions” on welfare as well as tax and spending.
Here are some of the ways in which it will directly affect you and your money. 
Typically, September's Consumer Prices Index (CPI) measure of inflation, which this time is 1.7%, is the benchmark for raising benefits the following April.
The amount paid in some benefits should, by law, rise at least at the same rate as prices.
That includes all the main disability benefits, such as personal independence payment, attendance allowance and disability living allowance, as well as carer’s allowance.
Universal credit, the most common benefit which is claimed by seven million people, is among other benefits also expected to rise in line with inflation, but that is a decision for ministers.
It means that the standard allowance of universal credit, for a single person aged under 25, is expected go up by £5.30 a month to about £317.
For a couple aged over 25, the rise is likely to be £10.50 to £628 a month, according to investment platform AJ Bell.
The total amount received in universal credit depends significantly on your circumstances, such as earnings, children, or disabilities. Adding 1.7% to your current benefit amount should give a fairly accurate estimate of what you will receive in April.
About 58% of universal credit claimants are women, and 38% of the total are working.
Someone receiving attendance allowance, or the highest rate of personal independence payment, will see an increase of about £1.85 a week in April.
The increase in benefits is less than the 6.7% rise last April, which reflected the higher cost of living then.
September's inflation figure was lower than expected, which means the increase in benefits is set to be relatively small.
Next month, a rise in energy bills, which took effect at the start of this month, is expected to push the inflation rate back up again - too late for the link to benefits.
The government, specifically the work and pensions secretary (no doubt working very closely with the chancellor), can decide to set a higher rate of increase for benefits. Charities would welcome such a move, but it would be extremely unlikely.

Listen to Newscast's take on what lower inflation means for you on BBC Sounds.
The rise in the state pension in April is governed not only by inflation, but by what is known as the triple lock.
Under that arrangement, the state pension goes up each year by either 2.5%, inflation, or earnings growth - whichever is the highest figure.
This time around, the latest data has confirmed the highest is earnings growth - at 4.1%. This is expected to mean:
It is worth noting that millions of pensioners will lose their winter fuel payment, worth up to £300, as a result of a government cut.
As inflation is now below the Bank of England's 2% target, it paves the way for further interest rate cuts.
That would make borrowing money less expensive, but could mean lower returns for savers.
Analysts say there is now a greater likelihood of an interest rate cut by the Bank in December, after a widely expected reduction from the current level of 5% in November.
That could give mortgage lenders more confidence to reduce the interest they charge on new fixed-rate home loans.
Many people face higher monthly repayments, as rates are higher than many were accustomed to for a decade.
Separate official figures show that people who are renting a home are paying 8.4% more than a year ago - displaying the continued financial squeeze on tenants.
It would be hoped that lower mortgage rates could ease some pressure on landlords and, in turn, limit rent rises for tenants.
There remains some nervousness among borrowers and consumers in general about what will happen in the Budget, announced by Chancellor Rachel Reeves on 30 October.
Government sources have told the BBC that she is looking to make tax rises and spending cuts to the value of £40bn.
Lower inflation can help or hinder the government.
It means that the Treasury may be left with a slightly lower than expected benefits bill.
However, lower inflation and wage rises could drag fewer people into higher rates of tax, even though the thresholds have been frozen.
This means the government could also gather less in tax as a result.
Government sources insist the move would not constitute a breach of Labour's manifesto tax pledge.
Content creators are going viral for renovating abandoned Japanese homes for low prices - but is all as it seems?
The council votes to urge the prime minister to reverse the "dreadful" Winter Fuel Payment changes.
The government promise a “radical” shake-up of the welfare system to help people out of work due to sickness.
Chancellor Rachel Reeves will set out the government's financial plans for the next year.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Job coaches could visit mental health patients when they are in hospital to help them get back to work, the government has said.
Trials of employment advisers giving CV and interview advice in hospitals produced "dramatic results", Work and Pensions Secretary Liz Kendall told the BBC.
She said a wider roll out would form part of her drive to shrink the UK's annual disability and incapacity benefits bill. 
But disability rights campaigners expressed concerns about the proposals, saying they have the potential to worsen someone's mental health.
"It is ridiculous to try and turn a hospital, a place of care and support into a business setting," said Mikey Erhardt, campaigner at Disability Rights UK.
James Taylor, executive director of strategy at disability equality charity Scope, added: “We need to see evidence that work coaches being sent to visit seriously ill people works, and doesn’t cause distress."
The cost of disability benefits specifically is projected to surge almost a third in the next four to five years, according to the Institute for Fiscal Studies.
It predicted the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP) would spend £63bn by 2028-29, a jump from £48bn for 2023-24.
“I want to see those costs coming down, because I want to have people able to work, to get on in their work, which is good for them," Kendall told BBC News in an exclusive interview.
She indicated some people will lose their benefits, saying the "benefit system can have a real impact on whether you incentivise or disincentivise work".
Kendall praised projects in Leicester and at the Maudsley Hospital in Camberwell, in south-east London, which offered employment support - such as training on CV writing and interviews - to people with serious mental health conditions, including on hospital wards.
"The results of getting people into work have been dramatic, and the evidence clearly shows that it is better for their mental health," she said.
However, disability rights campaigner Erhardt said he would like to see the evidence of the trials.
"It is hugely inappropriate to be considering subjecting people who experience mental ill-health and distress to a CV check-up," he said.
Minesh Patel, associate director of policy and campaigns at Mind, added: “We welcome this much-needed spotlight on mental health hospitals [but] we’re still waiting to see the full details of the scheme and results of the trials.
“Right now, too many people with the most serious mental health problems are left more traumatised by their stay in hospital. If we want people to join or rejoin the workforce, they need safe and compassionate care that helps them truly get better."
The move by the government comes as figures suggest benefits will rise by 1.7% next April. September's inflation data is normally used to calculate how much many benefits go up by.
That is less than the current level of wage growth, and also less than April's expected rise in the state pension of 4.1% which is governed by the so-called triple lock.
Most benefits rose by 6.7% in April this year, in line with the inflation rate a year ago.
The amount paid in some benefits should, by law, rise at least in line with prices.
They include all the main disability benefits, such as personal independence payment, attendance allowance and disability living allowance, as well as carer’s allowance.
Others, including the universal credit, received by seven million people, are expected to rise in line with the inflation rate, but that is a decision for ministers.
However, the DWP is preparing a new employment white paper, for release around the time of the Budget and spending review later this month, which will outline its plans for reform of certain benefits, including who might receive them.
Kendall said she believed British society had become "sicker" and that the UK was the only country with advanced economies "whose employment rate has not gone back to pre-pandemic levels".
According to official figures released yesterday for the period from June to August, 21.8% of people are considered "economically inactive", meaning they are aged between 16 to 64 years old, not in work or looking for a job.
The figure has fallen marginally from the May to July period, but it remains at close to a decade-high after rising during the pandemic.
"There is clear evidence we are really struggling with health problems," Kendall added. 
She also urged employers to “think differently” about workers with mental health conditions to offer flexibility to support and retain workers with health problems.
Kendall also told the BBC job centres would be transformed by merging them with the national careers service and using AI. 
She suggested the face-to-face work would remain for the people “who really need it”, but “more personalised support using AI” for others, expanding on an idea introduced by her predecessor Stride.
She also suggested that giving powers to regional mayors would help match unemployed people more closely with local vacancies.
This echoes calls from Manchester Mayor Andy Burnham to hand control of job centres over to his regional government.
A newly-imposed law does not apply to Northern Ireland, so what does that mean for staff and employers?
Pollock Lifts employs about 175 people at its base in the Trooperslane Industrial Estate in County Antrim.
Charities say obesity is not a major problem when finding work as a weight loss drug trial is announced.
Expectations of a rate cut next month increase as pay growth slows to its lowest rate for more than two years.
Figures are showing a drop in unemployment rate and uptake in the number of people on company payrolls
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
The tactics of an increasingly professional shoplifting gang which has stolen at least £73,000 of goods from supermarkets across the UK have been revealed to the BBC.
Usually operating in groups of three, the gang members wear bluetooth headsets to communicate and warn each other if security guards are watching them.
Wheeling a trolley or carrying a supermarket basket, they blend in with shoppers as they walk down the alcohol aisle, casually taking champagne bottles off the shelves.
Then, one gang member will deliberately set off the security alarm to distract staff, while another simply walks out of the store with their stolen goods.
“It’s like a mafia-style operation. It’s run like a business,” says Sarah Bird from the National Business Crime Solution (NBCS) - an organisation which works with 100 businesses to tackle retail crime.

The criminals have been dubbed “the champagne gang” by the organisation, as it is the main item they have focused on stealing.
The gang “took full advantage” of a champagne shortage in mainland Europe 18 months ago, says Mrs Bird, caused by a post-Covid surge in demand and the failure of some crops. It meant a stronger black market, she says.
The group has a clear hierarchy with people at the top who instruct, she says, and a stream of employees who get paid.
“They travel to a specific place, they have a shopping list of things they need to steal. They steal the goods and get a day rate,” says Mrs Bird, head of local services at the NBCS.
The sophisticated shoplifting operation carried out by the champagne gang is being replicated by other criminal groups across the country.
The NBCS says it is tracking 63 organised criminal groups across the UK who have stolen at least £2.4m of goods in five years. Of these, 26 groups originate from the UK and Ireland and the rest predominantly from Eastern European countries.
The champagne gang originates from Romania and is responsible for 60 shoplifting incidents across the UK - from Gateshead to Bournemouth - according to NBCS data.
They came onto the NBCS’s radar in early 2023, but have since started swiping other types of alcohol and meat to serve a new demand.
The group changes tactics when new technology comes into the market that might impact their operation.
“They were originally using trolleys to take goods out the stores,” says Mrs Bird. “However retailers invested in trolley wheel technology to stop the trolleys at certain points in the stores.
“So they’ve started to now use baskets and bags to remove the goods.”
While the gang typically operates in a group of three, during one theft in Harrogate, North Yorkshire, there were at least seven members in the shop.
“We believe they took the opportunity in the Harrogate store as a training day for the new recruits - showing them the ropes and then effectively putting them to work,” says Mrs Bird.
“If they’re caught, they’re disposable. Generally speaking if they’re arrested and charged they’ll be bailed and quite often they’ll move back to their country - in this case to Romania.”
Only two members of the group have been prosecuted so far, according to the NBCS.
It is not only the thieves who end up back in Romania - it is believed the stolen goods end up there too, she says.
Intelligence, including from ANPR cameras - Automatic Number Plate Recognition - suggests the gang’s vehicles drive to Europe with the goods inside.
“This acts as an effective supply chain. The goods are moved from the UK to the continent to be sold in the likes of Romania.”
Retailers have repeatedly warned that shoplifting gangs are helping to fuel the rise in retail crime - and it is hitting shoppers in their pockets.
Shoplifting added £133 to the cost of an average UK household's annual shopping bill, according to the Centre for Retail Research.
Browns department store in Beverley, East Yorkshire, is being targeted by gangs who are getting smarter - its manager, Sarah Walker, says.
In March, one gang stole perfume from her store and within 90 minutes had targeted another Browns shop, 30 miles away in York.
“They’ve done research on the market where they’re going, they’ve looked at shops that have got the products that they need. It’s calculated,” Mrs Walker says.
Staff watch as gangs of four to six people of both sexes enter the shop, knowing exactly what to target.
“These gangs are intimidating, they can be young, and to put my staff under that vulnerability it’s hard,” says Mrs Walker.
“You don’t expect to come to work and be pushed and shoved out the way for someone who has got a shopping list - it’s organised crime and it’s a hit to our business.”
Mrs Walker says she reports shoplifting incidents to the police but it often “falls on deaf ears” and no-one gets arrested.
She wants to see more information sharing between UK police forces.
Humberside Police said it had liaised with North Yorkshire Police and the forces believed the two incidents in Beverley and York were linked.
However, it said the suspects could not be identified from CCTV footage and therefore no arrests could be carried out.
The past year has seen more information sharing between forces, in the form of Project Pegasus, in the National Police Chief Council (NPCC), which is focused on serious organised shoplifting.
Shoplifting gangs are “very good at adapting” their methods, Steph Coombes, of the NPCC, tells the BBC.
A total of 60 arrests have been made under the operation in four months - impacting organised crime groups and individuals which account for £3.4bn of loss, she added.
BBC Verify looks at violent crime rates in the US following the release of new data from the FBI.
Lawrence Bishnoi has been linked to high-profile murders in India. Now Canada accuses him of crimes on their soil. 
Government funding for the Violence Reduction Unit is due to end but officials say it must continue.
A mother says there is disparity between sentences for killings that happen in public and in private.
More people are being prosecuted for dangerous driving thanks to a huge increase in footage submitted to police by the public.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
Chancellor Rachel Reeves is looking to make tax rises and spending cuts to the value of £40bn in this month’s Budget, government sources have told the BBC.
At a political cabinet meeting on Tuesday, Reeves told ministers that filling the "£22bn black hole inheritance from the previous government" would only be enough "to keep public services standing still".
Reeves is now drawing up plans to find £40bn in order to avoid real-terms cuts to departments, sources say, as first reported in the Financial Times and the Times. 
Reeves warned ministers there would be "difficult decisions on spending, welfare, and tax" to come in her Budget this month.
The chancellor is finalising details of her first Budget, to be announced on Wednesday 30 October.
She recently said there would be "no return to austerity" under this government and promised a boost to government investment, designed to kickstart growth.
The chancellor is setting herself a borrowing rule which means all day-to-day spending should be funded from taxes raised, not from borrowing. 
It is this rule which is binding the government’s hands, and why they are seeking some welfare savings as well as a series of tax rises at the Budget.
A HM Treasury spokesperson said: "We do not comment on speculation around tax changes outside of fiscal events."
In an interview with BBC Breakfast on Tuesday, the Prime Minister, Sir Keir Starmer, did not rule out a National Insurance increase for employers in the Budget.
Paul Johnson, director of the Institute for Fiscal Studies, told the BBC Radio 4's Today programme the "very big hole in public finances" had been long known about, but was downplayed during election campaigning earlier this year.
He suggested that some of the £40bn would most likely be covered by "slight changes in the fiscal rules" or by tax rises proposed by the government already.
"If they are looking for £20bn or £30bn of tax rises, in the end they will have no choice but to do something with income tax."
Treasury officials are reportedly exploring National Insurance on employer pension contributions to raise Budget revenue.
Employers pay NI at a rate of 13.8% on all employees' earnings above £175 per week, but pension contributions made by employers are currently exempt from the levy.
The prime minister side-stepped questions over whether Labour’s manifesto promise not to raise taxes for "working people" covered employers' NI too.
The Labour Party's 2024 manifesto ruled out raising taxes for "working people", such as National Insurance, income tax and VAT.
On Monday, Reeves said Labour's election pledge not to increase NI on "working people" related to the employee element, as opposed to the sum paid by employers.
Leading business groups in the UK raised concerns over the potential tax rise, warning that it would "hobble" economic growth and "hammer" the hospitality sector.
The £40bn figure is much higher than government has previously acknowledged, as ministers come to terms with the economic reality of delivering on their promise that there will be "no return to austerity".
So why mention it now? To mentally prepare the public for tax rises to come, and begin to set the parameters as to what to expect.
The prime minister has talked about how those with the "broadest shoulders" should bear the "heaviest burden".
There are two weeks to go until we see what that means. There will no doubt be plenty more pitch-rolling in the days ahead.
Are you a small business owner concerned about a potential rise in national insurance? Email: haveyoursay@bbc.co.uk or WhatsApp: +44 7756 165803
Sign up for our Politics Essential newsletter to read top political analysis, gain insight from across the UK and stay up to speed with the big moments. It’ll be delivered straight to your inbox every weekday.
The council votes to urge the prime minister to reverse the "dreadful" Winter Fuel Payment changes.
It is not known how many people are likely to end up paying more under the government's plan.
In his first visit to the north east since taking office, the minister vowed support for North Sea workers.
Sir Keir Starmer has been urged to transfer powers to the Scottish government to help address labour shortages.
The ex-minister's clients are shown in a lobbying register for the first time since the general election.
Copyright 2024 BBC. All rights reserved.  The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read about our approach to external linking.
 
</content></news>